I want to talk to you about one thing
أريد أن أتحدث لك عن شيءٍ واحد
and just one thing only,
وهو شيءٌ واحدٌ فقط،
and this has to do with when people ask me,
وهذا متعلق ب عندما يسألني الناس،
what do you do?
ماذا تعمل؟
To which I usually respond,
غالبًا ما أجيب،
I do computer music.
أعمل في الموسيقى الحاسوبية.
Now, a number of people
الآن، سيتوقف عددٌ من الناس
just stop talking to me right then and there,
عن التحدث إلي فورًا،
and the rest who are left usually have
والبقية الذين قد رحلوا لديهم
this blank look in their eye,
هذه النظرة
as if to say, what does that mean?
كما لو أن أقول، ماذا يعني ذلك؟
And I feel like I'm actually depriving them
وأنا أشعر أنني في الواقع أحرمهم
of information by telling them this,
من المعلومات قبل أن نقول لهم هذا،
at which point I usually panic
وعند هذه النقطة أنا عادة أذعر
and spit out the first thing that comes to my mind,
واخرج أول ما يتبادر إلى ذهني،
which is, I have no idea what I'm doing.
الذي هو، ليس لدي فكرة عما أفعله.
Which is true.
وهذا صحيح.
That's usually followed by a second thought,
التي عادة ما تتبع بالفكرة الثانية،
which is, whatever it is that I'm doing,
التي هي، لا يهم ما هو الذي أفعله،
I love it.
المهم اني أحبها.
And today, I want to, well,
واليوم، أريد أن،
share with you something I love,
أشاطرك شيئًا أحبه،
and also why.
وأيضا لماذا.
And I think we'll begin with just this question:
و اعتقد اننا سنبدأ مع هذا السؤال فقط .
What is computer music?
ما هي الموسيقى الحاسوبية ؟
And I'm going to try to do my best to provide a definition,
ساحاول ان ابذل قصارى جهدي لأقدم تعريف،
maybe by telling you a story
ربما باخبارك قصة
that goes through some of the stuff
تذهب خلال بعض الشيء
I've been working on.
الذي كنت اعمل عليه
And the first thing, I think, in our story
و اول شيء، في قصتنا
is going to be something called ChucK.
سيكون هناك شيئًا ما يدعى تشاك .
Now, ChucK is a programming language for music,
الآن، تشاك هو لغة برمجة للموسيقى،
and it's open-source, it's freely available,
و المصدر مفتوح، و هو متاح مجانًا
and I like to think that it crashes equally well
أحب ان اعتقد انه تحطم جيد بالتساوي
on all modern operating systems.
في كل أنظمة التشغيل الحديثة.
And instead of telling you more about it,
و بدلا من اخبارك المزيد عنه،
I'm just going to give you a demo.
أنا فقط سأمنحك عرض.
By the way, I'm just going to nerd out
بالمناسبة، سأكون مهووسًا
for just a few minutes here,
لعدة دقائق فقط هنا،
so I would say, don't freak out.
لذا اود قول، لا تفزع.
In fact, I would invite all of you to join me
في الحقيقة،اود ان ادعوك لتنضم معي
in just geeking out.
في هوّسي.
If you've never written a line of code before in your life,
إذا لم تكتب سطر برمجي "كود" من قبل في حياتك،
do not worry.
لا تقلق.
I'll bet you'll be able to come along on this.
اراهن انك ستكون قادر على فهم هذا.
First thing I'm going to do is to make
أول شيء سوف اعمله هو ان اصنع
a sine wave oscillator,
موجة جيبية متذبذبة،
and we're going to called the sine wave generator
و سوف ندعو مولِد الموجة الجيبية
"Ge."
"غا" " Ge"
And then we're going to connect "Ge" to the DAC.
ثم سنربط "Ge" مع ال"DAC".
Now this is kind of the abstraction
الآن هذا نوع من الغموض
for the sound output on my computer. Okay?
بالنسبة لأداة اخراج الصوت على حاسوبي. حسنا؟
So I've connected myself into the speaker.
لذا ربطت نفسي مع السماعة.
Next, I'm going to say my frequency
بعد ذلك، سوف اقول ترددي
is 440 hertz,
هو 440 هيرتز،
and I'm going to let time advance
و سوف ادع الوقت يتقدم
by two seconds through this operation.
لثانيتين خلال هذا العملية.
All right, so if I were to play this --
حسنا، اذا لعبت هذه ــ
(Tone) —
( نغمة)--
you would hear a sine wave at 440 hertz for two seconds.
سمعت موجة جيبية في 440 هيرتز في ثانيتين
Okay, great. Now I'm going to copy and paste this,
حسنا،عظيم.الآن سانسخ والصق هذه،
and then just change some of these numbers,
و ساغير فقط بعض هذه الارقام،
220.5, 440 I shall leave it as that,
220.5،440 ساتركها كذلك،
and .5 and 880.
و 5. و 880.
By doubling the frequency,
مع مضاعفة التردد،
we're actually going up in successive octaves,
في الواقع نحن سنرفع الاوكتافات المتعاقبة،
and then we have this sequence --
ثم لدينا هذا الاصوات
(Tones) — of tones.
(نغمات) - للنغمات.
Okay, great, now I can imagine creating
حسنا، رائع، الآن استطيع تخيل صنع
all kinds of really horrible
كل الانواع من الموجات الجيبية
single sine wave pieces of music with this,
المنفردة الفظيعة حقًا للموسيقى مع هذه،
but I'm going to do something that computers are really good at,
لكن سافعل شيئا ما الحواسيب حقًا رائعة فيه
which is repetition.
الذي هو التكرار
I'm going to put this all in a while loop,
سوف اضع كل هذا في حلقة
and you actually don't need to indent,
واقعا لا تحتاج الى مسافة
but this is purely for aesthetic reasons.
بادئة، لكن هذا لأسباب جمالية بحتة
It's good practice.
انها تجربة جيدة
(Tones) —
(نغمات)
that's going to go on for a while.
سيؤدي الى عملها لمدة.
In fact, it's probably not going to stop
انها على الارجح لن تتوقف
until this computer disintegrates.
حتى يتحطم هذا الكمبيوتر.
And I can't really empirically prove that to you,
و انا لا استطيع عمليًا اثبات ذلك لك،
but I hope you'll believe me when I say that.
لكن اتمنى ان تصدقني حين اقول ذلك.
Next, I'm going to replace this 220
بعد ذلك، سأبدل هذه 220
by math.random2f.
برقم عشوائي.
I'm going to generate a random number
انا سأنتج رقم عشوئي
between 30 and 1,000 and send that
بين 30 و 1،000 و ارسل ذلك
to the frequency of me.
الى ترددي.
And I'm going to do this every half a second.
و ساعمل هذا كل نصف ثانية.
(Tones)
(نغمات)
Let's do this every 200 milliseconds.
دعنا نعمل هذا كل 200 ملي ثانية.
One hundred.
مــئــة.
(Tones)
(نغمات)
All right.
حسنا.
At this point, we've reached something
في هذه النقطة توصلنا لشيء ما.
that I would like to think of as
و الذي افكر به هو
This is, to me, the sound that mainframes
(ضحك)
are supposed to be making
من المفترض ان يكون لمن
when they're thinking really hard.
يفكرون بصعوبة حقا.
It's this sound, it's like,
انه هذا الصوت، انه مثل
the square root of five million.
الجذر التربيعي من 5 ملايين.
So is this computer music?
اذا هل هذه الموسيقى الحاسوبية؟ نعم،أظن ذلك
Yeah, I guess by definition,
حسب التعريف، انها
it's kind of computer music.
نوع من الموسيقى الحاسوبية.
and using ChucK,
و استخدام تشاك،
we've actually been building instruments
في الواقع بنينا أدوات
in the Stanford Laptop Orchestra,
في أوركسترا الحاسوب المحمول ستانفورد،
based right here at Stanford Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics.
مقرها هنا في مركز ستانفورد لبحوث الحاسوب
Now the Laptop Orchestra is an ensemble of laptops,
الآن اوركسترا هي مجموعة متكاملة
humans and special hemispherical speaker arrays.
البشر و خاصة نظم مكبرات الصوت النصف كروي.
Now the reason we have these
الآن سبب لدينا أولاء
is so that for the instruments that we create
من اجل الادوات التي انشئناها
out of the laptop, we want the sound to come
من الحواسيب المحمولة ، نريد الصوت ان يأتي
out of somewhere near the instrument
من مكان ما بالقرب من الأداة
and the performer,
و المؤدي لذلك
kind of much like a traditional, acoustic instrument.
نوع من ذلك بكثيرا مثل أداة صوتية تقليدية.
Like, if I were to play a violin here,
مثلا، اذا عزفت الكمان هنا،
the sound would naturally not come out of
الصوت طبيعيًا لن يخرج من
the P.A. system, but from the artifact itself.
نظام .P.A ، لكن من القطعة نفسها.
So these speakers are meant to emulate that.
لذا أولاء مكبرات الصوت مجهزة لمحاكاة ذلك.
In fact, I'm going to show you
في الحقيقة، سوف اعرض لك
how we actually built them.
كيف نبنيهم نحن في الواقع .
The first step is to go to IKEA
أول خطوة هي ان تذهب الى IKEA
and buy a salad bowl.
وتشتري وعاء سلطة.
This is an 11-inch Blanda Matt.
هذه 11 بوصة بلاندا مات
That's the actual name,
ذلك هو الاسم الفعلي
and I actually use one of these
في الواقع استخدم واحدًا منهم
to make salad at home as well, I kid you not.
لاعمل سلطة في المنزل كذلك، انا امزح لا.
And the first step is you turn it upside down,
و اول خطوة هي ان تقلبها رأسا على عقب،
and then you drill holes in them,
و ثم ستحفر ثقوب فيهم
six holes per hemi,
6 ثقوب لكل نصف كروي،
and then make a base plate,
ثم اعمل لوحة قاعدة،
put car speaker drivers in them
ضع مكبرات الصوت فيهم
along with amplifiers in the enclosure,
جنبًا الى جنب مع مكبرات الصوت في العلبة،
and you put that all together and you have
و ستضع كل ذلك معًا و لديك
these hemispherical speaker arrays.
هؤلاء صفوف مكبرات الصوت النصف كروية.
Add people, add laptops,
أضف الناس،أضف الحواسيب المحمولة،
you have a laptop orchestra.
لديك الحاسوب المحمول اوركسترا.
And what might a laptop orchestra sound like?
كيف سيبدو صوت أوركسترا الحاسوب ؟
Well, let me give you a demonstration
حسنًا، دعني امنحك شرح
of about 200 instruments we've created so far
عن 200 أداة بناؤها حتى الآن
for the Laptop Orchestra.
لاوركسترا الحاسوب المحمول .
And what I'm going to do is actually come over to this thing.
و ما سأفعله هو في الواقع سآتي الى شيء.
This thing I have in front of me
هذا الشيء لدي أمامي
actually used to be a commodity gaming controller
واقعًا اعتاد ان يكون سلعة متحكم الالعاب
called a Gametrak.
يدعى "غيم تراك"
This thing actually has a glove you can put on your hands.
هذا الشيء به قفاز تستطيع وضع يديك فيه
It's tethered to the base,
المربوط بالقاعدة،
and this will track the position of your hands
و هذا سيحدد موقع يديك
in real time.
في الوقت الحقيقي.
It was originally designed as a golfing controller
تم تصميمها في الاصل كوحدة تحكم الغولف
to detect the motion of your swing.
لكشف حركة التأرجح.
That turned out to be a rather large
التي تحولت لتكون كبيرة لحد ما
commercial non-success,
تجارية عديمة النجاح،
at which point they slashed prices to 10 dollars,
عند هذه النقطة خفضت الاسعار الى 10 دولار،
at which point computer music researchers
باحثو الموسيقى الحاسوبية في هذه النقطة
said, "This is awesome!
قالو: " هذا مذهل!!
So let me show you one instrument we've created,
اذا دعني أعرض لك أداة واحدة انشئناها،
one of many, and this instrument
واحدة من العديد، و هذه الأداة
is called "Twilight,"
تدعى "الشفق."
and it's meant to go with this metaphor
و المفترض ان تذهب مع محاكاة
of pulling a sound out of the ground.
سحب صوت خارج الأرض.
So let me see if this will work.
لذا دعني ارى اذا سيعمل هذا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And put it back.
و ضعها مرة أخرى
And then if you go to the left,
بعد ذلك اذا ذهبت الى اليسار،
right,
اليمين،
it sounds like an elephant in pain.
صوتها مثل فيل مُتألم.
Turn it just a bit.
نشغلها قليلًا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
It's like a hovering car.
انها مثل سيارة تحلق.
Okay.
حسنًا.
This third one is a ratchet-like interaction, so
هذا ثالث واحد هو مفتاح يشبه التفاعل ،لذا
let me turn it up.
دعني اشغلها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So it's a slightly different interaction.
اذا انه نوعًا ما تفاعل مختلف
The fourth one is a drone.
رابع واحد هو أزيز
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And finally, let's see,
و أخيرًا ، دعنا نرى،
this is a totally different interaction,
هذا تفاعل مختلف كليا
and I think you have to imagine that there's
و اعتقد انه يجب عليك تخيل ذلك هناك
this giant invisible drum sitting right here on stage,
الطبل الغير مرئي العملاق هنا على المسرح.
and I'm going to bang it.
وانا سوف اضربه.
(Drum)
(طبل)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So there we go, so that's one of many instruments
ها هناك نحن ،لذا تلك واحدة من عدة أدوات
in the Laptop Orchestra.
في الحاسوب المحمول اوركسترا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لك.
And when you put that together,
و عندما تضع تلك مع بعض،
you get something that sounds like this.
سوف يخرج صوت مثل هذا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Okay, and so, I think from the experience
حسنًا،اعتقد من تجربة
of building a lot of instruments for the Laptop Orchestra,
بناء الكثير من الأدوات لاوركسترا
and I think from the curiosity of wondering,
اعتقد من حب الاستطلاع و التساؤل
what if we took these
ماذا لو اخذنا هؤلاء
hopefully expressive instruments
الأدوات التعبيرية المتأمل منها
and we brought it to a lot of people,
و جلبتها الى كثير من الناس
plus then a healthy bout of insanity —
بالإضافة الى نوبة صحية من الجنون ــــ
put those three things together —
ضع الاشياء الثلاثة مع بعض ــ
led to me actually co-founding a startup company
قاد لي واقعًا الى شركة تاسيس التعاون
in 2008 called Smule.
في 2008 تدعى "سميول"
Now Smule's mission is to create
الآن مهمة سميول هي ان ينشئ
expressive, mobile music things,
يعبر، اشياء الموسيقى المحمولة
and one of the first musical instruments
واحدة من أول الأدوات الموسيقية
we created is called Ocarina.
بنيناها هي تدعى "أوكارينا"
And I'm going to just demo this for you real quick.
و انا فقط سأعرض هذا بسرعة حقيقة
So Ocarina —
اذا أوكارينا ـ
(Music) —
(موسيقى) ــ
is based on this ancient flute-like instrument
تعتمد على الناي القديم مثل أداة
called the ocarina,
تدعى أوكارينا
and this one is the four-hole English pendant configuration,
هذه رابع ثقب في تكوين القلادة الانجليزية،
and you're literally blowing into the microphone
انت حرفيا تنفخ في الميكروفون
to make the sound.
لتصنع الصوت.
And there's actually a little ChucK script
واقعًا هناك سيناريو تشاك القليل
running in here that's detecting
تدخل هنا وتلك تكشف عن
the strength of your blowing
قوة نفخك
and also synthesizing the sound.
و أيضا توليف الصوت.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And vibrato is mapped to the accelerometer,
ويتم تعيين الاهتزاز الى التسارع،
so you can get —
لذا يمكنك ان تسمع ـ
(Music)
(موسيقى)
All right. So let me play a little ditty for you,
حسنًا.لذا دعني اعزف اغنية قصيرة من أجلك،
a little Bach.
قليلا من (Bach).
And here, you'll hear a little accompaniment with the melody.
و هنا ، ستسمع قليلا من مرافقة اللحن.
The accompaniment actually follows the melody,
المرافقة واقعًا تتبع اللحن
not the other way around.
ليس حول الطريق الآخر.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And this was designed
و هذه كانت مصممة
to let you take your time
لتدعك تاخذ من وقتك
and figure out where your expressive space is,
و لمعرفة اين يكون مساحة تعبيرك،
and you can just hang out here
و يمكنك ان تعرضها هنا
for a while, for a really dramatic effect, if you want,
لمدة ، لتأثير درامي حقًا، اذا أردت
and whenever you're ready —
و حتى تكون مستعد ـ
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And on these longer notes,
و في هؤلاء النوتات،
I'm going to use more vibrato
سوف استخدم المزيد من الاهتزاز
towards the end of the notes
نحو نهاية النوتات
to give it a little bit more of an expressive quality.
لتمنح أكثر قليلًا من نوع التعبير.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Huh, that's a nice chord to end this excerpt on.
(ضحك)
Thank you.
شكرًا.
So I think a good question to ask about Ocarina is,
لذا اعتقد انه سؤال جيد عن اوكارينا
is this a toy or it an instrument? Maybe it's both,
هل هذه لعبة او أداة؟ ربما هي كلاهما،
but for me, I think the more important question is,
لكن بالنسبة لي، اعتقد اهم سؤال هو،
is it expressive?
هل هي معبرة؟
And at the same time, I think
نفس الوقت،اعتقد
creating these types of instruments
صنع تلك
and its place for how we make music.
و مكانها من اجل كيف نصنع الموسيقى.
Apparently, for example,
كما يبدو،على سبيل المثال،
not that long ago, like only a hundred years ago —
قبل مئة سنة فقط
that's not that long in the course of human history —
في مسار تاريخ البشرية
used to make music together
استخدمت لصنع الموسيقى معا
as a common form of entertainment.
كنوع من الترفيه.
I don't think that's really happening
أنا لا أعتقد أن ذلك يحدث
that much anymore.
هذا قبل الراديو،
You know, this is before radio, before recording.
و قبل التسجيل الصوتي.
In the last hundred years, with all this technology,
في آخر مئة سنة،
we now have more access to music
لدينا الآن أكثر من الوصول إلى الموسيقى
as listeners and consumers,
كمستمعون و كمستهلكون
than ever before.
من قبل حتى الآن
I'm not sure why that would be.
أنا لست متأكد لماذا
Maybe it's because it's too easy just to hit play.
ربما لأنها سهلة مجرد ان تبدأ العزف
And while listening to music is wonderful,
و في حين الاستماع للموسيقى هو رائع
there's a special joy to making music
و هنالك متعة خاصة لصنع الموسيقى
that's all its own.
كل ذلك ملكها.
And I think that's one part
و اعتقد ذلك جزء واحد
of the goal of why I do what I do
من الهدف من سبب فعل ما افعل
is kind of to take us back to the past a little bit. Right?
نوعا ما، هي تأخذنا إلى الماضي قليلا صحيح؟
Now, if that's one goal, the other goal
الآن إذا ذلك هدف واحد الهدف الآخر
is to look to the future and think about
هو أن ترى المستقبل و تفكر عن
what kind of new musical things can we make
ما نوع الأشياء الموسيقية التي نستطيع صنعها
that we don't perhaps yet have names for
ربما حتى الآن ليس لدينا أسماء لها
that's enabled by technology, but ultimately
إنها ممكنة بالتقنية، لكن في نهاية المطاف
might change the way that humans make music.
يمكن أن تغير طريقة عمل البشر للموسيقى
And I'll just give you one example here,
و سامنحك مثالا واحدا هنا
and this is Ocarina's other feature.
و هذه ميزة اوكارينا الأخرى
This is a globe,
هذه كرة أرضية
and here you're actually listening
و هنا في الواقع أنت تسمع
to other users of Ocarina
المستخدمون الآخرون لاوكارينا
blow into their iPhones to play something.
انفخ في آيفوناتهم اعزف شيء ما
This is "G.I.R." from Texas,
هذا G-I-R من تكساس
They're all playing pretty,
كلهم يعزفون ببراعة
somewhat minimal music here.
الحد الأدنى للموسيقى هنا
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And the idea with this is that, well,
و الفكرة مع هذا هي، حسنا
technology should not be foregrounded here,
التقنية يجدر بها ألا تكون امامنا هنا
we've actually opened this up.
في الواقع اول ما فتحناه.
The first thought is that, hey, you know
اول فكرة خطرت، كما تعرف
there's somebody somewhere out there
هنالك شخص ما في مكان ما هناك
playing some music,
يعزف بعض الموسيقى
and this is a small but I think important
و هذا صغير لكن اعتقد
human connection to make
التواصل البشري مهم لجعل
that perhaps the technology affords.
ذلك ربما يتيح التقنية
As a final example,
كمثال أخير
and perhaps my favorite example,
و ربما مثالي المفضل
is that in the wake of the 2011 earthquake
انه في صحوة زلزال 2011
and tsunami disaster in Japan,
و كارثة التسونامي في اليابان،
a woman reached out in one of our singing apps
امرأة وصلت الى احد تطبيقات الغناء
to try to get people to join in to sing with her
لتحاول أن ينضم الناس معها في الغناء
on a version of "Lean on Me."
في لحن "lean on Me" .
Now, in these apps, there's this thing that allows
الآن في هؤلاء التطبيقات، هناك شيء الذي
any user to add their voice
يسمح لاي مستخدم لاضافة صوتهم
to an existing performance by any other user
الى الأداء الحالي بأي مستخدم آخر او مجموعة
or group of users,
من المستخدمين
so in some sense, she's created this kind of
لذا اسست هذه
global ad hoc corral of strangers,
المجموعة العالمية المخصصة من الغرباء
and within weeks, thousands of people
مع مرور الأسابيع،الالاف من الناس
joined in on this,
انضموا في هذه،
and you can kind of see people coming from all around the world
و تستطيع رؤية الناس يأتون من حول العالم
and all these lines converging on the origin
و جميع الخطوط تتلاقى على الأصل
where the first rendition of the song was sung,
حيث أول عرض للأغنية غنّيت،
and that's in Tokyo.
في طوكيو.
And this is what it sounds like when there's 1,000 people.
و هذا مثل عندما يكون هنالك ألف شخص.
This is 1,000 voices.
هذا ألف صوت.
(Recording) ♪ Sometimes in our lives ♪
(تسجيل) ،احيانا في حياتنا،
♪ We all have pain, we all have sorrow ♪
، كلنا نشعر بالألم ، كلنا نشعر بالحزن،
♪ But if we are wise ♪
، لكن لو كنا حكماء،
♪ We know that there's always tomorrow ♪
،سنعرف ان هنالك دائما غد،
♪ Lean on me ♪
،تتكئ عليّ،
♪ When you're not strong ♪
♪ عندما لن تكون قوياً ♪
♪ And I'll be your friend ♪
♪ سأكون صديقك ♪
♪ I'll help you carry on ♪
♪أنا سوف أساعدك على الاستمرار في ♪
♪ For it won't be long ♪
♪سوف لن تكون طويلة ♪
♪ Till I'm gonna need ♪
♪ حتى أحتاج إلى ♪
♪ Somebody to lean on ♪
♪ شخص ما ليتكئ على ♪
♪ Just lean on — ♪
♪ فقط تتكئ على - ♪
Is this computer music?
هل هذة موسيقى حاسوبية؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Was that computer music?
هل كانت تلك موسيقى حاسوبية؟
Yeah, I guess so; it's something that you really
نعم، أظن ذلك؛ إنّها حقًا شيءٌ
couldn't have done without computers.
لا يمكنك القيام به دون الحواسيب.
But at the same time, it's also just human,
لكن في نقس الوقت، إنّها انسانية فحسب،
and let's just finally return to the first question:
ودعونا أخيرًا تعود إلى السؤال الأول:
What is computer music?
ما هي الموسيقى الحاسوبية؟
And I think that the catch here is that,
وأعتقد المسألة هنا، على الأقل بالنسبة لي،
It is about people.
إنّها عن الناس.
It's about how we can use technology
إنّها حول كيفية استخدام التقنية
to change the way we think
لتغيير الطريقة التي نفكّر بها
and do and make music,
والطريقة التي نعمل ونصنع بها الموسيقى،
And with that, I want to say,
وبهذا أريد أن أقول،
this is computer music, and thank you for listening.
هذه هي الموسيقى الحاسوبية،
(Applause)
(تصفيق)